<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coral on The Portal Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/coral/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coral on The Portal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/coral/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sargassum</title>
      <link>/post/sargassum/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sargassum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/esri.leaflet/esri-leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/esri.leaflet/esri-leaflet-bindings.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/leaflet.fullscreen.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/Leaflet.fullscreen.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-it&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t spent any time on a boat in the ocean, you may not be familiar with this habitat. Unlike the other habitat types highlighted on this blog, &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; is primarily found offshore (except when it washes ashore in huge mats, which occasionally happens in the USA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassumOffshore.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Sargassum line can stretch for miles across the ocean surface. Image: NOAA Teacher at Sea, Carol Schnaiter&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; line can stretch for miles across the ocean surface. Image: NOAA Teacher at Sea, Carol Schnaiter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;, also called Gulf weed, is a type of large brown seaweed that floats thanks to gas-filled bladders called pneumatocysts. It can attach to rocks or reefs, like kelp but smaller, or be free-floating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassum_kelp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Side-by-side of kelp (left, image courtesy of NOAA Fisheries) and Sargassum (right, image courtesy of Art Howard, NAPRO).&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Side-by-side of kelp (left, image courtesy of NOAA Fisheries) and &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; (right, image courtesy of Art Howard, NAPRO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two free-floating species found in the Gulf of Mexico, &lt;em&gt;Sargassum natans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sargassum fluitans&lt;/em&gt;. Neither species spend any of their life cycle attached to the seafloor and they reproduce solely by fragmentation, distinguishing them from all other seaweeds (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/1788092&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Deacon 1942&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0198014983900791&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stoner 1983&lt;/a&gt;). During fragmentation, a younger part of the plant breaks off from the rest of the plant and eventually develops into a mature, fully grown individual. Mosses reproduce via fragmentation, as do some cacti if they lose a a stem segment. Most &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; has a life span of a year or less, dying off in winter and being replenished the next year (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01431161003639660&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gower and King 2011&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-is-it&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where is it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good question! But a tough one to answer. Satellite imagery can provide snapshots in time of the distributions of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;, but because its location is heavily influenced by wave, current, and wind action, &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; mats are always on the move. Such satellite imagery has been analyzed and data suggest that the northwest Gulf of Mexico may act as a major nursery area between March and June, before the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; is funneled out of the Gulf into the Atlantic in July (&lt;a href=&#34;http://precedings.nature.com/documents/1894/version/1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gower and King 2008&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassumMap.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Seasonal distribution of Sargassum.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Seasonal distribution of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;this-map-is-available-in-a-story-map-produced-by-grid-arendal-which-can-be-found-here&#34; class=&#34;section level6&#34;&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;* This map is available in a story map produced by GRID-Arendal which can be found &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://grid-arendal.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapJournal/?appid=f616ec1db45f4e898970bd448b190f50&#34;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; Scientists are working on modeling the anticipated location of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; in an effort to prepare decision makers for beaching events. Sargassum Watch System, the culmination of some of this work, uses satellite data and numerical models to track &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; tracking is almost real time, and is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://optics.marine.usf.edu/projects/SaWS.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-of-sargassum-in-fishery-ecosystems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Role of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; in Fishery Ecosystems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pelagic open ocean is a pretty barren place, offering very little protection for larval and juvenile fishes that live in the water column, which is where &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; comes into play. &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; provides shelter on the surface of the ocean for about 120 species of fish and 120+ species of invertebrates. Gray triggerfish are an important Gulf of Mexico reef fish and really depend on &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;. While the adults are caught on reefs, juveniles spend anywhere from four to seven months in the pelagic environment, using &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; as protection from predators (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00028487.2011.545002?journalCode=utaf20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Simmons and Szedlmayer 2010&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassumFish.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Small fishes living in the Sargassum. Image: NOAA.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Small fishes living in the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;. Image: NOAA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the juvenile fish that congregate in &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; mats, predators also use this habitat to feed. If you’ve done any dolphin (the fish, not the mammal) fishing you know that finding &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; is key to finding the fish. This is because dolphinfish eat the other small fish species hiding in the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;; the same is true for tuna and other pelagic fish species. &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; contributes significantly to fishery ecosystems beyond being an important habitat; other ocean animals like birds, turtles, and marine mammals use it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/turtleSargassum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sargassum provides essential habitat for species like turtles. Image: NOAA Ocean Explorer.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; provides essential habitat for species like turtles. Image: NOAA Ocean Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011, 2014, and 2015 large amounts of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; washed ashore in the Caribbean and onto some beaches in the United States; it was such a substantial event that it was reported on by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsweek.com/2015/07/10/sargassum-ruining-beaches-texas-tobago-347735.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Newsweek in 2015&lt;/a&gt;. When &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; shows up at your favorite ocean-front spot it looks dirty, covering up the beautiful sandy beaches and it can smell pretty bad when it bakes in the sun. But it’s important to remember that such material can provide nutrients to beaches and can even help protect land by strengthening sand dunes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassumBeach.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sargassum on the beach. Image: David Horner, NPS&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Sargassum on the beach. Image: David Horner, NPS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-sargassum&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Threats to &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;, like other habitat types described in this blog, is threatened by natural and human-caused degradation. Extreme weather events like hurricanes can break up &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; mats, cause them to strand on beaches, or sink altogether. Habitat fragmentation or disappearance entirely can be very problematic for species that depend on &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; in an otherwise structure-less environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropogenic (human-caused) threats to &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; are numerous and include obvious things like pollution, but also some disturbances that may not immediately come to mind, like shipping traffic. For those living in the Gulf states, when you think of pollution to floating habitat, an oil spill is probably your first thought. When oil comes into contact with &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; it gets caught up in the floating mats and impacts the both the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; itself, and the species associated with it. The direct impacts of oil to Sargassum include restricting growth and sinking. If the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; dies from prolonged oil exposure and sinks it can bring associated oil to the bottom of the ocean where it can negatively impact animals there also. Oil vapors inhaled by species on the surface (like dolphins, turtles, and birds) can be toxic, as can contact with the oil directly, whether it be dissolved or as a surface slick, which would impact animals beneath the surface as well (like fish and crabs). For more information on oil spills and &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; check out this post from &lt;a href=&#34;https://response.restoration.noaa.gov/about/media/what-happens-when-oil-spills-meet-massive-islands-seaweed.html&#34; target = &#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NOAA’s Office of Response and Restoration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/sargassumOil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of the potential impacts of an oil spill on Sargassum and associated marine life in the water column. Image: NOAA Response and Restoration&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Illustration of the potential impacts of an oil spill on &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; and associated marine life in the water column. Image: NOAA Response and Restoration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; washed up on the beach or out in the ocean, you’ve probably seen garbage tangled up in it. Since most plastics float and get carried by currents, wind, and wave action, the same as &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt;, they tend to get mixed up together. Plastic pollution is primarily dangerous for animals in the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; and less so for the &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; itself. Up to 52% of sea turtles worldwide have eaten plastic debris, and olive ridley turtles, while not present in the Gulf of Mexico, are at particular risk because of their feeding habitats (&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/gcb.13078/abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Schuyler et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;). Many species of sea turtle (including olive ridleys) eat jellyfish, and plastic bags can look very similar floating through the ocean. In addition to the harm of ingesting plastics, animals can also get caught in things like fishing nets, plastic bags or balloons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/turtleNet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diver releasing a sea turtle caught in a derelict fishing net. Image: NOAA Marine Debris Program&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Diver releasing a sea turtle caught in a derelict fishing net. Image: NOAA Marine Debris Program&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shipping traffic is another less obvious disruptor of &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; environments. Cargo and tanker vessels are common in the Gulf of Mexico and they have the potential to disrupt &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; communities in several ways: 1) physical disruption of moving through &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; mats, 2) pollutant (sewage, oil, chemicals) discharge, and 3) disruptive noise generated by the ships (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sargassoseacommission.org/storage/documents/Sargasso.Report.9.12.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Laffoley et al. 2011&lt;/a&gt;). More research is needed to quantify the impacts of shipping vessels on &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thorough report on threats to &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; is available from The Sargasso Sea Alliance and can be found &lt;a href = &#34;http://www.sargassoseacommission.org/storage/documents/Sargasso.Report.9.12.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}},&#34;fullscreenControl&#34;:{&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topleft&#34;,&#34;pseudoFullscreen&#34;:false}},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/Canvas/World_Dark_Gray_Base/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/Canvas/World_Dark_Gray_Reference/Mapserver/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false,&#34;attribution&#34;:&#34;MarineCadastre.gov | ESRI, HERE, Garmin, NGA, USGS, NPS&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addEsriDynamicMapLayer&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;https://coast.noaa.gov/arcgis/rest/services/MarineCadastre/2013TankerVesselDensity/MapServer&#34;,null,&#34;Tanker&#34;,{&#34;format&#34;:&#34;png24&#34;,&#34;transparent&#34;:true,&#34;f&#34;:&#34;json&#34;,&#34;attribution&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;front&#34;,&#34;useCors&#34;:true},null,null]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addEsriDynamicMapLayer&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;https://coast.noaa.gov/arcgis/rest/services/MarineCadastre/2013CargoVesselDensity/MapServer&#34;,null,&#34;Cargo&#34;,{&#34;format&#34;:&#34;png24&#34;,&#34;transparent&#34;:true,&#34;f&#34;:&#34;json&#34;,&#34;attribution&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;front&#34;,&#34;useCors&#34;:true},null,null]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLayersControl&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[[&#34;Tanker&#34;,&#34;Cargo&#34;],[],{&#34;collapsed&#34;:false,&#34;autoZIndex&#34;:true,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topright&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLegend&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;colors&#34;:[&#34;#e83134&#34;,&#34;#fafa87&#34;,&#34;#2892c7&#34;],&#34;labels&#34;:[&#34;high&#34;,&#34;&#34;,&#34;low&#34;],&#34;na_color&#34;:null,&#34;na_label&#34;:&#34;NA&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;bottomleft&#34;,&#34;type&#34;:&#34;unknown&#34;,&#34;title&#34;:&#34;Amount of Vessel Traffic&#34;,&#34;extra&#34;:null,&#34;layerId&#34;:null,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;info legend&#34;}]}],&#34;setView&#34;:[[25.15,-89.87],5,[]]},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;this-map-illustrates-the-density-of-shipping-vessel-cargo-and-tanker-traffic-in-the-gulf-of-mexico-in-2013.-more-information-on-the-data-used-to-create-this-map-can-be-found-here.&#34; class=&#34;section level6&#34;&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;* This map illustrates the density of shipping vessel (cargo and tanker) traffic in the Gulf of Mexico in 2013. More information on the data used to create this map can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalog.data.gov/dataset?tags=shipping&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deacon, G. E. R. 1942. The Sargasso Sea. The Geographical Journal. 99: 16-28.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gower, J. and S. King. 2008. Satellite images show the movement of floating &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; in the Gulf of Mexico and Atlantic Ocean. Available from Nature Precedings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gower, J. F. R. and S. A. King. 2011. Distribution of floating &lt;em&gt;Sargassum&lt;/em&gt; in the Gulf of Mexico and the Atlantic Ocean Mapped using MERIS. International Journal of Remote Sensing, 32(7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laffoley, D.d’A., H. S. J. Roe, M. V. Angel, J. Ardron, N. R. Bates, I. L. Boyd, S. Brooke, K. N. Buck, C. A. Carlson, B. Causey, M. H. Conte, S. Christiansen, J. Cleary, J. Donnelly, S. A. Earle, R. Edwards, K. M. Gjerde, S. J. Giovannoni, S. Gulick, M. Gollock, J. Hallett,P. Halpin, R. Hanel, A. Hemphill, R. J. Johnson, A. H. Knap, M. W. Lomas, S. A. McKenna, M. J. Miller,P. I. Miller, F. W. Ming, R. Moffitt, N. B. Nelson, L. Parson, A. J. Peters, J. Pitt, P. Rouja, J. Roberts, J. Roberts, D. A. Seigel, A. N. S. Siuda, D. K. Steinberg, A. Stevenson, V. R. Sumaila, W. Swartz, S. Thorrold, T. M. Trott and V. Vats. 2011. The protection and management of the Sargasso Sea: The golden floating rainforest of the Atlantic Ocean. Summary Science and Supporting Evidence Case.Sargasso Sea Alliance, 44 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schuyler, Q. A., C. Wilcox, K. A. Townsed, K.R. Wedemeyer-Strombel, G. Balazs, E. van Sebille and B. D. Hardesty. Risk analysis reveals global hotspots for marine debris ingestion by sea turtles. Global Change Biology, 22(2): 567-576.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simmons, C. M. and S. T. Szedlmayer. 2010. Recruitment of age-0 gray triggerfish to benthic structured habitat in the northern Gulf of Mexico. Transactions of the American Fisheries Society, 140(1): 14-20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoner, A. W. 1983. Pelagic Sargassum: Evidence for a major decrease in biomass. Deep Sea Research, 30: 469-474.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seagrasses</title>
      <link>/post/seagrasses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/seagrasses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/leaflet.fullscreen.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/Leaflet.fullscreen.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;what-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly what they sound like, grasses that grow under water! While often mistaken for seaweed, they are actually more similar to the grass in your yard. They have roots, stems and leaves, and produce flowers and seeds, plus they need light to grow. Unlike your lawn though, they grow completely submerged in water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/seagrassFlounder2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Seagrass. Image: NOAA Fisheries&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Seagrass. Image: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are about 52 species of seagrass worldwide, growing as far north as the Arctic Circle, but around the Gulf Coast there are six. The distribution of the difference species varies based on their preferred range of salinity, turbidity, and light requirements, but I’ll get into that more in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most seagrasses produce asexually and sexually. Seagrass asexual reproduction is clonal, meaning that many of the plants in a seagrass meadow may appear to be individuals, but are actually a part of the same plant, with a network of underground rhizomes - which are like underground stems - supporting individual shoots. These shoots will all have the same genetic code too! This kind of growth is exhibited by terrestrial species such as aspen trees and blueberry bushes. Sexual reproduction occurs via pollination, but as you might imagine, there is a noticeable lack of bees under the sea, so pollination is aided by water movement; small invertebrates can help with this process as well. Seagrass seeds can be spread by water flow, but also by animals, such as fish and turtles, eating and excreting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/seaturtleNOAA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Turtle feeding on seagrass. Image: NOAA&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Turtle feeding on seagrass. Image: NOAA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses distribution is dictated by light, bottom type, and salinity requirements. Of the six seagrass species found in the Gulf, all six occur off the coast of Florida, and they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turtle Grass (&lt;em&gt;Thalassia testudinum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manatee Grass (&lt;em&gt;Syringodium filiforme&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoal Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halodule wrightii&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paddle Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halophila decipiens&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Star Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halophila engelmanni&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wigeon Grass (&lt;em&gt;Ruppia maritima&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these species are found Gulf-wide, in varying densities. Shoal grass and turtle grass are prevalent Gulf-wide; paddle grass is extensive in south Florida; star grass is common in Florida but is less common in the northern Gulf, only being found off of the Chandeleur Islands, Louisiana. You’d think manatee grass would only be in Florida, considering that’s the only place manatees can be found in the Gulf, but it also occurs in south Texas. Lastly, widgeon grass, which is common in estuaries that are heavily influenced by freshwater, is the only species that can grow in both freshwater and saline environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the map below to see the distribution of all seagrasses in the Gulf of Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}},&#34;fullscreenControl&#34;:{&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topleft&#34;,&#34;pseudoFullscreen&#34;:false}},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/World_Imagery/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/Reference/World_Boundaries_and_Places/Mapserver/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://portal.gulfcouncil.org/arcgis/rest/services/seagrass/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;minZoom&#34;:0,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:18,&#34;maxNativeZoom&#34;:null,&#34;tileSize&#34;:256,&#34;subdomains&#34;:&#34;abc&#34;,&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;tms&#34;:false,&#34;continuousWorld&#34;:false,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;zoomOffset&#34;:0,&#34;zoomReverse&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false,&#34;attribution&#34;:&#34;Commission for Environmental Cooperation | Esri, DigitalGlobe, GeoEye, Earthstar Geographics, CNES/Airbus DS, USDA, USGS, AeroGRID, IGN&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLegend&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;colors&#34;:[&#34;#e0e326&#34;],&#34;labels&#34;:[&#34;Seagrass&#34;],&#34;na_color&#34;:null,&#34;na_label&#34;:&#34;NA&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;bottomleft&#34;,&#34;type&#34;:&#34;unknown&#34;,&#34;title&#34;:null,&#34;extra&#34;:null,&#34;layerId&#34;:null,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;info legend&#34;}]}],&#34;setView&#34;:[[25.15,-89.87],5,[]]},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;these-data-were-collected-and-synthesized-by-the-commission-for-environmental-cooperation.-more-information-regarding-how-the-data-were-gathered-is-available-in-the-report-north-americas-blue-carbon-assessing-seagrass-salt-marsh-and-mangrove-distribution-and-carbon-sinks.-the-report-is-available-here&#34; class=&#34;section level6&#34;&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;* These data were collected and synthesized by the Commission for Environmental Cooperation. More information regarding how the data were gathered is available in the report, “North America’s Blue Carbon: Assessing Seagrass, Salt Marsh and Mangrove Distribution and Carbon Sinks”. The report is available &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://www3.cec.org/islandora/en/item/11664-north-america-s-blue-carbon-assessing-seagrass-salt-marsh-and-mangrove-en.pdf&#34;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-of-seagrasses-in-fishery-ecosystems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Role of Seagrasses in Fishery Ecosystems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses contribute to fishery ecosystems in crucial ways, one of which is quite similar to grass planted on a hillside, they prevent erosion. The complex structure of seagrasses - with their leaves, roots and rhizomes - reduce erosion, improve water clarity, and reduce the impact of waves on shore. Seagrasses also support macroalgae, but their relationship can be tenuous; if the nutrient concentrations in an estuary are too high, macroalgal blooms can smother seagrass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses also contribute to ecosystems via water quality improvement. The root system stabilizes sediments and slows water flow, reducing the likelihood that sediment will be dispersed in the water column. Estuarine environments can be heavily influenced by runoff, and seagrasses clear up the water by absorbing nutrients from runoff, but in some regions, seagrass can do the exact opposite. In nutrient poor environments, seagrasses can release nutrients - taken up from the soil - into the water through their leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses directly impact fisheries in the form of habitat and feeding. Seagrass beds provide shelter for small invertebrates and small or juvenile fish. This protection attracts larger fish and sharks which feed on the invertebrates and smaller fish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/turtleGrassSnails.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Snails on turtle grass. Image: NOAA Habitat&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Snails on turtle grass. Image: NOAA Habitat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!--*shark in seagrass pic from Lindsay (add this eventually)--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many species managed by the Gulf Council - like red drum, spiny lobster, and hogfish (to name a few) - use seagrasses at some point in their life cycle. Often as fish grow larger, the seagrasses no longer provide adequate protection from predators, the blades of grass no longer conceal them, and they move to larger structures; these can be reefs, hard bottom areas, or even artificial reefs, depending on the region of the Gulf. Once a fish has moved to its adult habitat, it may stay there for the remainder of its life, with all of its reproduction, feeding, and habitat needs being satisfied by these larger structures. Other species, like herbivores, will use a reef as shelter at night and spend the day foraging in nearby seagrass beds (&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4020-2983-7_20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Valentine and Duffy 2006&lt;/a&gt;), whereas smaller, reef-associated carnivores spend time on reefs during the day and forage in seagrass at night (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF00001467&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Burke 1995&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.publish.csiro.au/MF/MF97198&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cox et al. 1997&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34; http://sunzi.lib.hku.hk/ER/detail/hkul/3520238&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Blackmon 2005&lt;/a&gt;). It’s these relationships that intrinsically link seagrass and coral habitats, though these interactions are most pronounced in southern Florida and the Florida Keys, where both habitats are prevalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-seagrasses&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Threats to Seagrasses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrass coverage has declined in almost all areas of the Gulf since the 1950s; this stems from both natural and anthropogenic (human created) causes. Hurricanes, and the heavy wave action associated with them, can kill a significant proportion of seagrass beds, as was the case with Hurricane Camille which destroyed approximately 58% of the seagrasses in Mississippi Sound (Eleuterius and Miller 1976). Floods or droughts affect the amount of freshwater in estuaries, if the water becomes too salty or too fresh it can kill seagrass; as can increased sediment load or water turbidity. But these natural disturbances are much less harmful than the human activities associated with seagrass loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human activities causing seagrass loss include runoff which increases due to urban development, dredging and filling, and boat scaring. Runoff is problematic because of the pollution and nutrients entering the waterways. These cause turbidity and increased algal growth, which in turn reduce light penetration and eventual seagrass death. Coastal development and marine navigation require dredging and filling, which can cause physical destruction or burying of seagrass beds. Boat scaring is caused by the propeller on a boat, and is generally accidental, taking a shortcut across a channel or straying into a shallow area can result in prop scaring. The consequences of seagrass loss are numerous and can have impacts on the ecology and economy of an area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/propscarDamageNOAA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prop scar damage. Image: NOAA&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Prop scar damage. Image: NOAA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blackmon, D.C. 2005. Diel vertical migration of seagrass-associated benthic invertebrates: a novel escape mechanism that provides and allochthonous input of seagrass-based production to coral reef resident predators. Dissertation. University of South Alabama, Mobile, Alabama, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burke, N.C. 1995. Nocturnal foraging habitats of French and bluestriped grunts, &lt;em&gt;Haemulon flavolineatum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;H. sciurus&lt;/em&gt;, at Tobacco Caye, Belize. Environmental Biology of Fishes 42:365-374.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cox, C., J. Hunt, W.G. Lyons, and G.E. Davis. 1997. Nocturnal foraging of the Caribbean lobster(&lt;em&gt;Panularis argus&lt;/em&gt;) on offshore reefs of Florida, USA. Marine and Freshwater Research 48:671-679.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleuterius, L.N. and G.J. Miller. 1976. Observations on seagrass and seaweeds in Mississippi Sound since Hurricant Camille. Journal of Mississippi Academy of Science 21:58-63.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valentine, J.F. and J.E. Duffy. 2006. The central role of grazing in seagrass ecology. Pages 463-501 &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; T. Larkum, R. Orth, and C. Duarte, eds. Seagrasses: biolgy, ecology, and conservation. Springer, Dordrecht, Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mangroves</title>
      <link>/post/mangroves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mangroves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/leaflet.fullscreen.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/fullscreen/Leaflet.fullscreen.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-minimap/Control.MiniMap.min.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-minimap/Control.MiniMap.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-minimap/Minimap-binding.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;what-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mangroves are trees and shrubs that live in salty water. Not many trees can do this, which is readily apparent in some areas of coastal Louisiana, where saltwater intrusion has killed plants that aren’t well-equipped to live in such a hostile environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/dead_snags-large.png&#34; alt=&#34;Trees killed by saltwater intrusion. Image: Daniel Strain (Maryland Sea Grant)&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Trees killed by saltwater intrusion. Image: Daniel Strain (Maryland Sea Grant)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people imagine mangroves, they usually are thinking of red mangroves. These grow along the edge of the shoreline and have prop roots, which grow from the trunk down into the water and are exposed rather than covered in soil the way most plant roots are. Prop roots help provide stability to red mangroves and supply oxygen to underground roots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/redmangroves.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Red Mangroves. Image: NOAA Fisheries&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Red Mangroves. Image: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides red mangroves, there are 80 other described species, but only three others that are prevalent into Gulf coastal areas. These are black mangroves, white mangroves, and buttonwood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black mangroves live in areas higher above sea level than red mangroves. They have horizontal roots with projections called pneumatophores and their roots are exposed to air when tides are out. These mangroves are the type showing up in some of the northern Gulf states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/blackmangroves.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Black Mangroves. Image: Collier County Sea Grant&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Black Mangroves. Image: Collier County Sea Grant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White mangroves and buttonwood live in more upland areas than either the black or red mangroves. They are adapted to tolerate salty soil, but are rarely exposed to submersion in water, because of this, they do not have aerial roots like the other two species. In general, they look very similar to a shrub you might have in your yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/whitemangroves.png&#34; alt=&#34;White Mangroves. Image: Miami-Dade Sea Grant&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;White Mangroves. Image: Miami-Dade Sea Grant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mangroves live at the transition from sea to land, and are an integrall component of estuarine ecosystems, but if you live in Alabama you probably haven’t seen any there. They are usually found in areas that have regular tidal flow, some freshwater, and low to moderate wave energy (think channels in southern Florida and the Florida Keys). Their distribution is limited by freezing temperatures, which is why they are uncommon in the northern Gulf states. However, black mangroves, which are more cold tolerant, can be found on the Chandeleur Islands off Louisiana. They’ve also started popping up on the Mississippi Barrier islands (&lt;a href=&#34;http://goms.disl.org/assets/goms_disl/uploads/toc/2011_2030/goms-31-01-79-82.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Scheffel et al. 2013&lt;/a&gt;), and scientists suspect that as the global climate continues to warm, black mangroves will continue their spread north in the Gulf of Mexico (&lt;a href=&#34;https://repositories.tdl.org/tamug-ir/handle/1969.3/19073&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sherrod and McMillan 1985&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12237-010-9358-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pickens and Hester 2010&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/2/723.abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cavanaugh et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now though, mangroves are most prevalent in central and southern Florida and southern Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see if there are any mangroves near you, check on the interactive map below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}},&#34;fullscreenControl&#34;:{&#34;position&#34;:&#34;topleft&#34;,&#34;pseudoFullscreen&#34;:false}},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/World_Imagery/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/Reference/World_Boundaries_and_Places/Mapserver/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://portal.gulfcouncil.org/arcgis/rest/services/mangrove/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;minZoom&#34;:0,&#34;maxZoom&#34;:18,&#34;maxNativeZoom&#34;:null,&#34;tileSize&#34;:256,&#34;subdomains&#34;:&#34;abc&#34;,&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;tms&#34;:false,&#34;continuousWorld&#34;:false,&#34;noWrap&#34;:false,&#34;zoomOffset&#34;:0,&#34;zoomReverse&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false,&#34;attribution&#34;:&#34;Commission for Environmental Cooperation | Esri, DigitalGlobe, GeoEye, Earthstar Geographics, CNES/Airbus DS, USDA, USGS, AeroGRID, IGN&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addLegend&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[{&#34;colors&#34;:[&#34;#e61eb1&#34;],&#34;labels&#34;:[&#34;Mangroves&#34;],&#34;na_color&#34;:null,&#34;na_label&#34;:&#34;NA&#34;,&#34;opacity&#34;:1,&#34;position&#34;:&#34;bottomleft&#34;,&#34;type&#34;:&#34;unknown&#34;,&#34;title&#34;:null,&#34;extra&#34;:null,&#34;layerId&#34;:null,&#34;className&#34;:&#34;info legend&#34;}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addMiniMap&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[null,null,&#34;bottomleft&#34;,100,100,19,19,-5,false,false,false,false,false,false,{&#34;color&#34;:&#34;#ff7800&#34;,&#34;weight&#34;:1,&#34;clickable&#34;:false},{&#34;color&#34;:&#34;#000000&#34;,&#34;weight&#34;:1,&#34;clickable&#34;:false,&#34;opacity&#34;:0,&#34;fillOpacity&#34;:0},{&#34;hideText&#34;:&#34;Hide MiniMap&#34;,&#34;showText&#34;:&#34;Show MiniMap&#34;},[]]}],&#34;setView&#34;:[[25.9,-82.1],7,[]]},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;this-data-was-collected-and-synthesized-by-the-commission-for-environmental-cooperation.-more-information-regarding-how-the-data-was-gathered-is-available-in-the-report-north-americas-blue-carbon-assessing-seagrass-salt-marsh-and-mangrove-distribution-and-carbon-sinks.-the-report-is-available-here&#34; class=&#34;section level6&#34;&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;* This data was collected and synthesized by the Commission for Environmental Cooperation. More information regarding how the data was gathered is available in the report, “North America’s Blue Carbon: Assessing Seagrass, Salt Marsh and Mangrove Distribution and Carbon Sinks”. The report is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www3.cec.org/islandora/en/item/11664-north-america-s-blue-carbon-assessing-seagrass-salt-marsh-and-mangrove-en.pdf&#34;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-of-mangoves-in-fishery-ecosystems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Role of Mangoves in Fishery Ecosystems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first, and most obvious, role of mangroves in fisheries ecosystems are as nursery areas. Many coral reef associated fish, and some species managed by the Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council, start their lives in the mangroves. The prop roots of red mangroves provide protection and feeding habitat for goliath grouper, red grouper, gag, cobia, gray snapper, red drum, and king and Spanish mackerel, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/fishMangrovesNOAA2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Fish swimming in mangrove roots. Image: NOAA&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Fish swimming in mangrove roots. Image: NOAA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another function of mangroves, and most estuarine vegetation, is in carbon sequestration, which is just a fancy way of saying that mangroves remove CO2 from the atmosphere and store it in their soil. Maybe you can see where this is going, but less CO2 in the atmosphere means less CO2 available to contribute to ocean acidification and, unless you’ve been living under a rock, you’ve probably heard that ocean acidification is a large contributor to coral bleaching (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/105/45/17442.abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Anthony et al. 2008&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/318/5857/1737.full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hoegh-Guldberg et al. 2007&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, the removal or deforestation of mangroves can release that CO2 right back into the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting and relatively recent (2014) discovery is that mangrove habitats may provide some coral species refuge in an increasingly hostile ocean environment. In Hurricane Hole, St. John, USVI, researchers surveyed coral communities growning near mangrove habitats, and compared the prevalence of bleaching in corals that were shaded by mangroves to those that were not. &lt;em&gt;Colpophyllia natans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Diploria labyrinthiformis&lt;/em&gt; colonies were the most abundant reef building corals in Hurricane Hole and these were doing well despite declines in abundance on St. John reefs. None of the shaded colonies of &lt;em&gt;C. natans&lt;/em&gt; were bleached, compared to 10.5% of unshaded colonies, and 34.2% of &lt;em&gt;D. labyrinthiformis&lt;/em&gt; shaded colonies were bleached, compared to 66.1% of unshaded colonies (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biogeosciences.net/11/4321/2014/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yates et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do the mangroves provide shade, which reduces coral exposure to photosynthetically active radiation, but also buffer declines in water pH (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biogeosciences.net/11/4321/2014/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yates et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These mangrove habitats may reduce stress and increase survivabily for corals that are threatened by rising water temperatures and increased ocean acidification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-mangroves&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Threats to Mangroves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most threats to mangroves are human-caused, and because of the locations where they reside, these threats are particularly pronouned. Coastal areas are prime real estate, and as such, are subject to heavy development pressure. Impounding and ditching for mosquito control, reductions in freshwater inflows, clearing, and dredge and fill activities associated with navigation and the aforemetioned coastal development are all threats facing mangroves (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi/20001PIB.PDF?Dockey=20001PIB.PDF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Duke and Kruczynski 1992&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulfcouncil.org/wp-content/uploads/March-2004-Final-EFH-EIS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GMFMC 2004&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pollution, specifically oil, fertilizers, and pesticides/herbicides can negatively impact mangroves. Oil by coating their roots which limits oxygen transport, herbicides have been shown to cause defoliation and may be lethal to seedlings (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi/2000ZT9M.PDF?Dockey=2000ZT9M.PDF&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Teas 1976&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony, K. R. N., D. I. Kline, G. Diaz-Pulido, S. Dove, and O. Hoegh-Guldberg. 2008. Ocean acidificiation causes bleaching and productivity loss in coral reef builders. PNAS 105(45): 17442-17446.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cavanaugh, K. C., J. R. Kellner, A. J. Forde, D. S. Gruner, J. D. Parker, W. Rodriguez, and I. C. Feller. 2014. Poleward expansion of mangroves is a threshold response to decreased frequency of extreme cold events. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 111(2):723-727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duke, T. and W. L. Kruczynski. 1992. The status and trends of emergent and submerged vegetated habitats of the Gulf of Mexico coastal waters, USA. EPA 800-R-92-003. Stennis Space Center, Mississippi. 161 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GMFMC. 2004. Final Environmental Impact Statement for the Generic Essential Fish Habitat Amendment to the following fishery management plans of the Gulf of Mexico (GOM): Shrimp Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Red Drum Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Reef Fish Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Stone Crab Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Coral And Coral Reef Fishery of the Gulf Of Mexico, Spiny Lobster Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico and South Atlantic, and the Coastal Migratory Pelagic Resources of the Gulf of Mexico And South Atlantic. Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council, Tampa, Florida, 682 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoegh-Guldberg, O., P. J. Mumby, A. J. Hooten, R. S. Steneck, P. Greenfield, E. Gomez, C. D. Harvell, P. F. Sale, A. J. Edwards, K. Caldeira, N. Knowlton, C. M. Eakin, R. Iglesias-Prieto, N. Muthiga, R. H. Bradbury, A. Dubi, and M. E. Hatziolos. 2007. Coral reefs under rapid climate change and ocean acidification. Science 318: 1737-1742.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pickens, C. N., and M. W. Hester. 2011. Temperature tolerance of early life history stages of black mangrove &lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;: Implications for range expansion. Estuaries and Coasts 34:824-830.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheffel, W. A., K. L. Heck Jr., J. Cebrian, M. Johnson, and D. Byron. 2013. Range expansion of black mangroves (&lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;) to the Mississippi Barrier Islands. Gulf of Mexico Science 31(1/2): 79-82.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherrod, C. L. and C. McMillan. 1985. The distributional history and ecology of mangrove vegetation along the northern Gulf of Mexico coastal region. Contributions in Marine Science 28:129-140.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teas, H. J. 1976. Herbicide toxicity in mangroves. EPA-600/3-76-004. Environmental Research Laboratory, Gulf Breeze, Florida. 42 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yates, K. K., C. S. Rogers, J. J. Herlan, G. R. Brooks, N. A. Smiley, and R. A. Larson. 2014. Diverse coral communities in mangrove habitats suggest a novel refuge from climate change. Biogeosciences 11: 4321-4337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
