<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Portal Blog</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Portal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Seagrasses</title>
      <link>/post/mangroves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mangroves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;what-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly what they sound like, grasses that grow under water! While often mistaken for seaweed, they are actually more similar to the grass in your yard. They have roots, stems and leaves, and produce flowers and seeds, plus they need light to grow. Unlike your lawn though, they grow completely submerged in water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrass pic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are about 52 species of seagrass worldwide, growing as far north as the Arctic Circle, but in Florida and around the Gulf Coast there are seven. The distribution of the difference species varies based on their preferred range of salinity, turbidity, and light requirements, but I’ll get into that more in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most seagrasses produce sexually and asexually. Their asexual reproduction is clonal, meaning that many of the plants in a seagrass meadow may appear to be individual, but are actually a part of the same plant, with a network of underground rhizomes supporting individual shoots. These shoots will all have the same genetic code too! This kind of growth is exhibited by terrestrial species such as aspen trees and blueberry bushes. Sexual reproduction occurs via pollination, but as you might imagine, there is a noticeable lack of bees under the sea, so pollinations is aided by water movement; small invertebrates can help with this process as well. Seagrass seeds can be spread by water flow, but also by animals, such as fish and turtles, eating and excreting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turtle in seagrass pic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seagrasses distribution is dictated by their light and salinity requirements. Of the six seagrass species found in the Gulf, all six occur in Florida, and they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turtle Grass (&lt;em&gt;Thalassia testudinum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manatee Grass (&lt;em&gt;Syringodium filiforme&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoal Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halodule wrightii&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paddle Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halophila decipiens&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Star Grass (&lt;em&gt;Halophila engelmanni&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wigeon Grass (&lt;em&gt;Ruppia maritima&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these species are found Gulf-wide, in varying densities. Shoal grass and turtle grass are prevalent Gulf-wide; paddle grass is extensive in south Florida; star grass is common in Florida but is less common in the northern Gulf, only being found off of the Chandeleur Islands, Louisiana; you’d think manatee grass was only in Florida, considering that’s the only place manatees can be found in the Gulf, but it also occurs in south Florida; and widgeon grass, which is common in estuaries that are heavily influenced by freshwater, it’s the only species that can growth in both freshwater and saline environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the map below to see the distribution of all seagrasses in the Gulf of Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-of-seagrasses-in-fishery-ecosystems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Role of Seagrasses in Fishery Ecosystems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-seagrasses&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Threats to Seagrasses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate Change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony, K. R. N., D. I. Kline, G. Diaz-Pulido, S. Dove, and O. Hoegh-Guldberg. 2008. Ocean acidificiation causes bleaching and productivity loss in coral reef builders. PNAS 105(45): 17442-17446.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cavanaugh, K. C., J. R. Kellner, A. J. Forde, D. S. Gruner, J. D. Parker, W. Rodriguez, and I. C. Feller. 2014. Poleward expansion of mangroves is a threshold response to decreased frequency of extreme cold events. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 111(2):723-727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duke, T. and W. L. Kruczynski. 1992. The status and trends of emergent and submerged vegetated habitats of the Gulf of Mexico coastal waters, USA. EPA 800-R-92-003. Stennis Space Center, Mississippi. 161 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GMFMC. 2004. Final Environmental Impact Statement for the Generic Essential Fish Habitat Amendment to the following fishery management plans of the Gulf of Mexico (GOM): Shrimp Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Red Drum Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Reef Fish Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Stone Crab Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Coral And Coral Reef Fishery of the Gulf Of Mexico, Spiny Lobster Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico and South Atlantic, and the Coastal Migratory Pelagic Resources of the Gulf of Mexico And South Atlantic. Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council, Tampa, Florida, 682 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O. Hoegh-Guldberg, P. J. Mumby, A. J. Hooten, R. S. Steneck, P. Greenfield, E. Gomez, C. D. Harvell, P. F. Sale, A. J. Edwards, K. Caldeira, N. Knowlton, C. M. Eakin, R. Iglesias-Prieto, N. Muthiga, R. H. Bradbury, A. Dubi, and M. E. Hatziolos. 2007. Coral reefs under rapid climate change and ocean acidification. Science 318: 1737-1742.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pickens, C. N., and M. W. Hester. 2011. Temperature tolerance of early life history stages of black mangrove &lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;: Implications for range expansion. Estuaries and Coasts 34:824-830.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheffel, W. A., K. L. Heck Jr., J. Cebrian, M. Johnson, and D. Byron. 2013. Range expansion of black mangroves (&lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;) to the Mississippi Barrier Islands. Gulf of Mexico Science 31(1/2): 79-82.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherrod, C. L. and C. McMillan. 1985. The distributional history and ecology of mangrove vegetation along the northern Gulf of Mexico coastal region. Contributions in Marine Science 28:129-140.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teas, H. J. 1976. Herbicide Toxicity in mangroves. EPA-600/3-76-004. Environmental Research Laboratory, Gulf Breeze, Florida. 42 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yates, K. K., C. S. Rogers, J. J. Herlan, G. R. Brooks, N. A. Smiley, and R. A. Larson. 2014. Diverse coral communities in mangrove habitats suggest a novel refuge from climate change. Biogeosciences 11: 4321-4337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mangroves</title>
      <link>/post/mangroves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mangroves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/jquery/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leafletfix/leafletfix.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-label/leaflet.label.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4-compressed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/Proj4Leaflet/proj4leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/leaflet-binding/leaflet.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;what-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mangroves are trees and shrubs that live in salty water. Not many trees can do this, which is readily apparent in some areas of coastal Louisiana, where saltwater intrusion has killed plants that aren’t well-equipped to live in such a hostile environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dead tree, marsh, Louisiana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people imagine mangroves, they usually are thinking of red mangroves. These grow along the edge of the shoreline and have prop roots, which grow from the trunk down into the water and are exposed rather than covered in soil the way most plant roots are. Prop roots help provide stability to red mangroves and supply oxygen to underground roots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/redmangroves.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Red Mangroves. Image: NOAA Fisheries&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Red Mangroves. Image: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides red mangroves, there are 80 other described species, but only three others that are prevalent into Gulf coastal areas. These are black mangroves, white mangroves, and buttonwood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black mangroves live in areas higher above sea level than red mangroves. They have horizontal roots with projections called pneumatophores and their roots are exposed to air when tides are out. These mangroves are the type showing up in some of the northern Gulf states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/blackmangroves.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Black Mangroves. Image: Collier County Sea Grant&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Black Mangroves. Image: Collier County Sea Grant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White mangroves and buttonwood live in more upland areas than either the black or red mangroves. They are adapted to tolerate salty soil, but are rarely exposed to submersion in water, because of this, they do not have aerial roots like the other two species. In general, they look very similar to a shrub you might have in your yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/whitemangroves.png&#34; alt=&#34;White Mangroves. Image: Miami-Dade Sea Grant&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;White Mangroves. Image: Miami-Dade Sea Grant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-are-they&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mangroves live at the transition from sea to land, and are an integrall component of estuarine ecosystems, but if you live in Alabama you probably haven’t seen any there. They are usually found in areas that have regular tidal flow, some freshwater, and low to moderate wave energy (think channels in southern Florida and the Florida Keys). Their distribution is limited by freezing temperatures, which is why they are uncommon in the northern Gulf states. However, black mangroves, which are more cold tolerant, can be found on the Chandeleur Islands off Louisiana. They’ve also started popping up on the Mississippi Barrier islands (Scheffel et al. 2013), and scientists suspect that as the global climate continues to warm, black mangroves will continue their spread north in the Gulf of Mexico (Sherrod and McMillan 1985; Pickens and Hester 2010; Cavanaugh et al. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now though, mangroves are most prevalent in central and southern Florida and southern Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see if there are any mangroves near you, check on the interactive map below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:672px;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;leaflet html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;crs&#34;:{&#34;crsClass&#34;:&#34;L.CRS.EPSG3857&#34;,&#34;code&#34;:null,&#34;proj4def&#34;:null,&#34;projectedBounds&#34;:null,&#34;options&#34;:{}}},&#34;calls&#34;:[{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/World_Imagery/MapServer/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]},{&#34;method&#34;:&#34;addTiles&#34;,&#34;args&#34;:[&#34;http://server.arcgisonline.com/ArcGIS/rest/services/Reference/World_Boundaries_and_Places/Mapserver/tile/{z}/{y}/{x}&#34;,null,null,{&#34;errorTileUrl&#34;:&#34;&#34;,&#34;noWrap&#34;:true,&#34;zIndex&#34;:null,&#34;unloadInvisibleTiles&#34;:null,&#34;updateWhenIdle&#34;:null,&#34;detectRetina&#34;:false,&#34;reuseTiles&#34;:false}]}],&#34;setView&#34;:[[25.15,-89.87],6,[]]},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-of-mangoves-in-fishery-ecosystems&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Role of Mangoves in Fishery Ecosystems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first, and most obvious, role of mangroves in fisheries ecosystems are as nursery areas. Many coral reef associated fish, and some species managed by the Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council, start their lives in the mangroves. The prop roots of red mangroves provide protection and feeding habitat for goliath grouper, red grouper, gag, cobia, gray snapper, red drum, and king and Spanish mackerel, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fish in mangroves pic – Lindsay B.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another function of mangroves, and most estuarine vegetation, is in carbon sequestration, which is just a fancy way of saying that mangroves remove CO2 from the atmosphere and store it in their soil. Maybe you can see where this is going, but less CO2 in the atmosphere means less CO2 available to contribute to ocean acidification and, unless you’ve been living under a rock, you know that ocean acidification is a large contributor to coral bleaching (Anthony et al. 2008; O. Hoegh-Guldberg et al. 2007). Unfortunately, the removal or deforestation of mangroves can release that CO2 right back into the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting and relatively recent (2014) discovery is that mangrove habitats may provide some coral species refuge in an increasingly hostile ocean environment. In Hurricane Hole, St. John, USVI, researchers surveyed coral communities growning near mangrove habitats, and compared the prevalence of bleaching in corals that were shaded by mangroves to those that were not. &lt;em&gt;Colpophyllia natans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Diploria labyrinthiformis&lt;/em&gt; colonies were the most abundant reef building corals in Hurricane Hole and these were doing well despite declines in abundance on St. John reefs. None of the shaded colonies of &lt;em&gt;C. natans&lt;/em&gt; were bleached, compared to 10.5% of unshaded colonies, and 34.2% of &lt;em&gt;D. labyrinthiformis&lt;/em&gt; shaded colonies were bleached, compared to 66.1% of unshaded colonies (Yates et al. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do the mangroves provide shade, which reduces coral exposure to photosynthetically active radiation, but also buffer declines in water pH (Yates et al. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These mangrove habitats may reduce stress and increase survivabily for corals that are threatened by rising water temperatures and increased ocean acidification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-mangroves&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Threats to Mangroves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most threats to mangroves are human-caused, and because of the locations where they reside, these threats are particularly pronouned. Coastal areas are prime real estate, and as such, are subject to heavy development pressure. Impounding and ditching for mosquito control, reductions in freshwater inflows, clearing, and dredge and fill activities associated with navigation and the aforemetioned coastal development are all threats facing mangroves (Duke and Kruczynski 1992; GMFMC 2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pollution, specifically oil, fertilizers, and pesticides/herbicides can negatively impact mangroves. Oil by coating their roots which limits oxygen transport, herbicides have been shown to cause defoliation and may be lethal to seedlings (Teas 1976).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate Change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony, K. R. N., D. I. Kline, G. Diaz-Pulido, S. Dove, and O. Hoegh-Guldberg. 2008. Ocean acidificiation causes bleaching and productivity loss in coral reef builders. PNAS 105(45): 17442-17446.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cavanaugh, K. C., J. R. Kellner, A. J. Forde, D. S. Gruner, J. D. Parker, W. Rodriguez, and I. C. Feller. 2014. Poleward expansion of mangroves is a threshold response to decreased frequency of extreme cold events. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 111(2):723-727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duke, T. and W. L. Kruczynski. 1992. The status and trends of emergent and submerged vegetated habitats of the Gulf of Mexico coastal waters, USA. EPA 800-R-92-003. Stennis Space Center, Mississippi. 161 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GMFMC. 2004. Final Environmental Impact Statement for the Generic Essential Fish Habitat Amendment to the following fishery management plans of the Gulf of Mexico (GOM): Shrimp Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Red Drum Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Reef Fish Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Stone Crab Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico, Coral And Coral Reef Fishery of the Gulf Of Mexico, Spiny Lobster Fishery of the Gulf of Mexico and South Atlantic, and the Coastal Migratory Pelagic Resources of the Gulf of Mexico And South Atlantic. Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council, Tampa, Florida, 682 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O. Hoegh-Guldberg, P. J. Mumby, A. J. Hooten, R. S. Steneck, P. Greenfield, E. Gomez, C. D. Harvell, P. F. Sale, A. J. Edwards, K. Caldeira, N. Knowlton, C. M. Eakin, R. Iglesias-Prieto, N. Muthiga, R. H. Bradbury, A. Dubi, and M. E. Hatziolos. 2007. Coral reefs under rapid climate change and ocean acidification. Science 318: 1737-1742.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pickens, C. N., and M. W. Hester. 2011. Temperature tolerance of early life history stages of black mangrove &lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;: Implications for range expansion. Estuaries and Coasts 34:824-830.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheffel, W. A., K. L. Heck Jr., J. Cebrian, M. Johnson, and D. Byron. 2013. Range expansion of black mangroves (&lt;em&gt;Avicennia germinans&lt;/em&gt;) to the Mississippi Barrier Islands. Gulf of Mexico Science 31(1/2): 79-82.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherrod, C. L. and C. McMillan. 1985. The distributional history and ecology of mangrove vegetation along the northern Gulf of Mexico coastal region. Contributions in Marine Science 28:129-140.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teas, H. J. 1976. Herbicide Toxicity in mangroves. EPA-600/3-76-004. Environmental Research Laboratory, Gulf Breeze, Florida. 42 pp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yates, K. K., C. S. Rogers, J. J. Herlan, G. R. Brooks, N. A. Smiley, and R. A. Larson. 2014. Diverse coral communities in mangrove habitats suggest a novel refuge from climate change. Biogeosciences 11: 4321-4337.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
